A Guide to the Loudoun County Oral History Project, 1975-1998
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Loudoun County Oral History Project 1975-1998
Thomas Balch Library
M 014, AV 008
This collection consists of oral history recordings and written transcripts of the recordings related to Loudoun County history and culture. These sound recordings were made on cassette tapes and include information on family histories, community histories, schooling, politics, and the socio-economic issues faced by families in Loudoun County. Many interviews also focus on specific topics including: the civil rights movement, integration of Loudoun County schools, and the Great Depression. The collection also includes photos of some of the interviewees. The collection is filed by format in 7 boxes. There are 3 boxes of transcripts and 4 boxes of cassettes. The date of each interview (transcript and tape) is included in the container list.
Loudoun County Public Library
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Loudoun County Public Library, Leesburg, VA
Alternative Form Available
Sound recordings: cassette tapes; digital files: (.wav format).
Accruals
2004.0078x; 2012.0156x
Historical Information
In the mid-1970s the first interviews for what became the Loudoun County Oral History Project were conducted with the purpose of interviewing Loudoun County locals in order to preserve the history, culture, and lifestyles of previous generations. Many oral histories were recorded between 1975 and 1978, however the project lost momentum and almost a decade elapsed before any other interviews were recorded. In the mid-1980s, the oral history project continued and recorded interviews from 1986 to 1992. A number of interviews were also recorded between 1994 and 1998. Eugene Scheel, a local historian and cartographer, conducted the majority of the interviews. Other interviewers who participated in the project include: Jane Sullivan, Vivian Chola, Barbara Dutton, and Loudoun Valley High School students. The individuals interviewed for the project included members of well-known Loudoun families such as Cockerill, Fry, Furr, Potts, Powell, and Purcell. Also interviewed were Important and notable individuals within the Loudoun County community including B. Powell and Agnes Harrison, Anna Hedrich, Louisa Hutchison, Basham Simms, Charles Blair Tavenner, and John W. Tolbert.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of oral history recordings and written transcripts of the recordings related to Loudoun County history and culture. These sound recordings were made on cassette tapes and include information on family histories, community histories, schooling, politics, and the socio-economic issues faced by families in Loudoun County. Many interviews also focus on specific topics including: the civil tights movement, integration of Loudoun County schools, and the Great Depression. The collection also includes photos of some of the interviewees. The collection is filed by format in 7 boxes. There are 3 boxes of transcripts and 4 boxes of cassettes. The date of each interview (transcript and tape) is included in the container list.
The oral history recordings are only accessible in digital format (.wav files), which can be transferred to a CD on request for in-library use. Prior arrangements are suggested to use the collection. Please contact library staff ahead of time.
NOTES: Inconsistent audio quality in cassettes. Not all oral history transcripts have cassette records.
Arrangement
Box: folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Loudoun County Oral History Project, 1975-1998 (M 014), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Technical Requirements
CD player and computer software: Roxio Creater and/or Windows Media Player
Related Material
Black History Committee Oral History Project, 2000-2006 (M 012), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA; Student Oral History Collection, 1981 (M 008), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Contents List
- (M 014)
  - Transcripts
    - Anti-Billboard and Zoning Ordinances, 1977
    - Arter, Violet E., 1989
    - Ball, Harvey MacDaniel "Mac" Jr., 1991
    - Berry, John E., 1977
    - Bodmer, John Perry, 1977
    - Brown, Bill, 1986
    - Butt, Robert, 1991
    - Carey, Alice, 1990
    - Carter, Rosa, 1991
    - Cockerill, Nancy, 1990
    - Compher, Charles E., 1977
    - Cooper, Garland, 1986
    - Cowart, Esther, 1986
    - Dillon, John, 1977
    - Divine, John, 1989
    - Divine, John, 1990
    - Downs, Erman C., 1977
    - Douglass, James E. "Ned", 1977
    - Emerick, Ruth, 1977
    - Fiske, William "Bill", 1989
    - Fletcher, Charles and Irene, 1990
    - Fowler, Virginia. 1989
    - Francis, Sydnor, 1990
    - Frazer, William P., 1978
    - Frazer, William P., 1991
    - Fry, Arthur S., 1976
    - Furr, Carl, 1977
    - Furr, Flossie, 1989
    - George, Clara, 1991
    - Green, Mary, n.d.
    - Grubb, Hugh, 1992
    - Hall, Clarence, n.d.
    - Harris, James, n.d.
  - Transcripts
    - Harrison, B. Powell and Agnes, 1992
    - Hatcher, Grover, 1989
    - Heaton, Elizabeth, 1989
    - Hedrich, Anna, 1989
    - Heffner, William J., 1991
    - Hersperger, Frances, 1989
    - Hess, George Roy, 1977
    - Hirst, Julian Terry, 1977
    - Hutchison, Leila, 1991
    - Hutchison, Thomas and Louisa, 1978
    - Iden, Earl Conway, 1977
    - Jackson, Robert Emmett, 1977
    - James, Geraldine Potts; East, Roberta Ellen James; East, Amy Elizabeth, 1993
    - Janney, Asa Moore, 1989
    - Johnson, Esther Lamar and Wire, Columbia Isabel Johnson, 1977
    - Kreiger, Kay, 1986
    - Lake, Dixie Lee Lodge, 1977
    - Legard, Sallie, 1990
    - Lindsey, Elizabeth, 1989
    - MacIntyre, Carl F., 1991
    - Majors, India, 1977
    - Mallory, Alberta, n.d.
    - Middleton, John, 1994
    - Monroe, Karlton and Mary, 1977; 1981
    - Myers, Douglas, 1978
    - Myers, Eliza, 1986
    - Newton, Dorothy Heaton, 1986
    - Owen, Elizabeth S., 1991
    - Owens, Anna Louise Titus, 1989
    - Owens, Ella, 1986
    - Painter, C.W., n.d.
    - Patterson, James, 1977
    - Pearson, Laura, 1990
    - Perry, Janet, 1993
    - Pickens, Vinton Liddell, 1990
  - Transcripts
    - Piggot, Shirley, 1977
    - Potts, Edwin and Lucy, 1991
    - Potts, Elizabeth, 1989
    - Potts, Jennings and Robert, 1991
    - Potts, Mary and Jennings, 1990
    - Potts, Thurston, 1977
    - Powell, Roger F., 1991
    - Purcell, Adelaide Constance, 1977
    - Purcell, Patience Adelaide, 1977
    - Purcellville Heritage Day, 1990
    - Reamer, Mary Katherine and Brittlbank, Ruth, 1975; 1977
    - Redmond, Isaac, 1977
    - Reid, Emma and Gracie, 1977
    - Riticor, Charles Franklin, 1977
    - Riticor, John Thomas, 1977
    - Rodgers, Jane and Cowart, Ester, n.d.
    - Roney, Delia, 1993
    - Scheetz, Sara Harrison, 1977
    - Simms, Basham, 1986
    - Simpson, Elizabeth Everhart, 1977
    - Smith, James, 1994
    - Rollison, John Thomas, 1977
    - Steele, R. Chamblin, 1989
    - Tavenner, Charles Blair, 1977
    - Tavenner, Fred Franklin, 1977
    - Taylor, Thomas E., 1991
    - Terrill, Esther Dogan, 1989
    - Tibbs, Allin, 1977
    - Valosio, Doris Flemming, 1992
    - Virts, Theodore Roosevelt and Fry, Jessie Alice Virts, 1992
    - Williams, Virginia L., 1992
- (AV 008)
  - Recordings
    - Boley, Robert (Master), 26 August 1998
    - Butt, Robert (Master), 30 October 1991
    - Carey, Alice (Master), 5 March 1990
    - Carey, Alice (Duplicate), 5 March 1990
    - Carter, Rosa (Master), 17 October 1991
    - Carter, Rosa (Duplicate), 17 October 1991
    - Carter, Violet (Master), 20 November 1989
    - Cockerill, Nancy (Master), 5 June 1990
    - Cockerill, Nancy (Duplicate), 5 June 1990
    - Fiske, William "Bill" (Master), 11 October 1989
    - Fowler, Virginia (Master), 10 April 1989
    - Francis, Sydnor Part 1 (Master), 14 November 1990
    - Francis, Sydnor Part 1 (Duplicate), 14 November 1990
    - Francis, Sydnor Part 2 (Master), 14 November 1990
    - Francis, Sydnor Part 2 (Duplicate), 14 November 1990
    - Frazer, William P. (Master), 18 December 1991
    - Furr, Flossie (Master), 25 October 1989
    - Furr, Flossie (Duplicate), 25 October 1989
  - Recordings
    - Gross, Helen (Master), 16 March 1997
    - Grubb, Hugh (Master), 30 September 1992; 21 October 1992
    - Grubb, Hugh (Duplicate), 30 September 1992; 21 October 1992
    - Harrison, B. Powell (Master), 19 August 1997
    - Hatcher, Grover (Master), 1 December 1989
    - Hedrich, Anna (Master), 17 October 1989
    - Heffner, William (Master), 15 May 1991
    - Hersperger, Frances (Master), 25 May 1989
    - Janney, Asa Moore (Master), 16 November 1989
    - Janney, Asa Moore (Duplicate), 16 November 1989
    - Legard, Sally (Master), March 1990
    - Legard, Sally (Duplicate), March 1990
    - Lindsey, Elizabeth Part 1 (Master), 4 May 1989
    - Lindsey, Elizabeth Part 2 (Duplicate), 4 May 1989
    - MacIntyre, Carl F. (Master), 25 May 1991
    - Middleton, John (Master), 5 May 1994
    - Myers, Eliza (Master), 2 October 1989
    - Myers, Eliza (Master), 5 June 1990
    - Myers, Eliza (Duplicate), 5 June 1990
  - Recordings
    - Anna Louise Titus Owens, Anna Louice Titus (Master), 27 October 1989
    - Owens, Elizabeth S. (Master), 17 December 1991
    - Pearson, Laura (Master), 28 August 1990
    - Perry, Mary Lee (Master), n.d.
    - Perry, Ruth (Master), 25 February 1997
    - Pickens, Vinton Liddell (Master), 25 July unknown
    - Potts, Elizabeth (Master), 18 April 1989
    - Potts, Jennings and Robert (Master), 16 October 1991
    - Potts, Jennings and Robert (Duplicate), 16 October 1991
    - Potts, Mary and Jennings (Master), 17 April 1990
    - Potts, Mary and Jennings (Duplicate), 17 April 1990
    - Powell, Roger (Master), 17 September 1991
    - Powell, Roger (Duplicate), 17 September 1991
    - Powell, Roger (Master), 13 December 1991
    - Powell, Roger (Duplicate), 13 December 1991
    - Purcellville Heritage Day (Master), 12 May 1990
    - Simms, Patricia (Master), n.d.
    - Simms, Robert (Master), 19 June 1990
    - Smith, James (Master), 19 March 1994
  - Recordings
    - Taylor, Thomas E. (Master), 20 February 1991
    - Terill, Esther Dogan (Master), 25 May 1989
    - Tolbert, John W. (Master), 14 August 1990
    - Tolbert, John W. (Master), 11 January 1995
    - Tolbert, John W. (Duplicate), 11 January 1995
    - Tolbert, John W. (Master), 2 March 1997
    - Tolbert, John W. (Duplicate), 2 March 1997
    - Virts, Theodore Roosevelt and Jessie Alice Virts Fry (Master), 14 January 1992